software engineering radio episode 91
careful in hanging on C++ this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at s e - radio dotnet s your radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every 10 days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our website for supporting the
porkchop
[Music]
hello this is another episode of
software engineering radio before we get
to the actual content of this episode I
do have a couple of announcements
thanks to Morocco as your radio now has
a webshop
it's a cafe press shop where you can buy
coffee marks and t-shirts and stuff with
the SU radio logo on it please go there
get it and do some advertising for su
radio so here is a heads up about the SU
radio get-together 2008 our open space
conference organized together with
debunked and sponsored by X magazine for
magazine for professional IT or magazine
for professional in robots you're
signing the conference will not be you
know it will not be presentations rather
it will be open space discussions so we
need you guys to come and bring with you
interesting discussion topics you
actually have to submit a little
position paper like a one-page small
pamphlet that talks about interesting
things we could discuss you should
submit this until June 1st to team and
se radio net and you'll get notified
until June 15th whether your paper is
accepted and whether hence you can come
to the conference we expect most papers
to be accepted unless we have way too
many registrations we actually need to
have about 70 people so why don't you go
to the se - radio dotnet website and on
the left side there is a link you can
click it and you'll get all the details
a nice PDF about the get-together yeah
well we're looking forward to actually
meeting you there this is our newest are
speaking and I'm interviewing Kelvin
Haney on C++ we were sitting at Europe
2007 in Bavaria having a good time
Catalan would you like to start by
saying a few words about yourself
hi yes Kevin honey I'm independent
consultant and trainer are based in the
UK
more generally the thing of interest I
guess is my background C++ I stumbled
into C++ sort of by accident
sometime around 1990 and growing
interest in object orientation at that
time pursued that to the point that it
was professionally useful and followed
through on a number of things writing
articles from the early 90s onwards
getting involved in the standardization
process through the British Standards
Institute and that was around the
mid-90s and pretty much that is
characterized my work I guess probably
the 1990s would be the right way of
looking at it I still have a great deal
of involvement with C++ projects but in
terms of my writing I guess that it's
not as C++ focus as it used to be and in
terms of standardization
I still stand back from the
standardization process a little bit but
I'm still partly involved with it yeah
we'll get into the standardization stuff
later on I guess um the reason we're
doing this episode on C++ is basically
that some of our listeners felt that we
were too java centric and sort of
treated C++ as being dead but well C++
is sort of alive and kicking is just not
edged as much represented in media so
would you say what do you say someone
told you C++ is obsolete is it well
there's two answers to that really other
there's the yes answer and there's the
no answer let's start with the yes
answer yes C++ is obsolete but so it's
Java so c-sharp so Ruby and you can pick
any language this is a standard language
water debate that doesn't generally help
people and tends to add more darkness
than light so where is it not aware
where is it not obsolete let's
understand that although we try
sometimes to simplify the idea of
programming language movements and say
everybody is doing language a and no
longer doing language B it's never that
simple and the landscape is at very
least two dimensional very complex
people in one corner don't necessarily
have anything to do with people
elsewhere their needs are often very
different get to arbitrary software
developers together and you will find
that their problem spaces are typically
quite different their basic vocabulary
set their development processes and so
on so in that sense C++ does not have
the role that it used to so it can be
said to be obsolete for some roles and
some of these have been displaced by in
places Java and in other places and by
c-sharp and in other places by languages
like Ruby and Python and so on and there
are also roles that C++ has never really
had any weight in and have grown in the
last ten years so it is very unlikely
you'll find a lot of web programmers
dealing with that but again that concept
of web programming really did not exist
in the form we recognize it now say 10
years ago but whereas c++ actually
picking up that's the interesting
question because as I said I do I still
do quite a lot of C++ work my work
divides between C++ Java a little bit of
c-sharp and various other languages
development process and design and so on
but the C++ stuff has shifted it is nota
support I'm not seeing many people
creating general application UI is in
C++ this might actually personally say
as a slight relief but what I am singh
doing is there is a a focus more and
more people are concerned with
applications that are reaching very
large scales high performance needs and
so on it's kind of the software that you
don't see the software that is routing
the traffic around the planet type
software there's and there's a great
deal of emphasis on that where people
care about performance they care about
the BI level control they care about
talking to the metal if you like but at
the same talking the same time talking
the metal is no longer a simple case of
lashing together some
assembler code or even C code you need a
way of building something to sustain
with a large team of developers and has
quite rich concepts and that appears to
be where C++ is gaining ground you have
the area of algorithm expression of
research which is not something that
other languages are necessarily
well-suited to in the mainstream and
there's a sort of growth in this area
where people are actually saying well if
I'm looking at some number crunching I
care about performance I care about the
structure of the algorithm these things
combine and languages like Java are
showing they're not really quite up to
this in their style their style actually
lies elsewhere their strengths are
elsewhere but you're not gonna find C++
developers sitting there doing
spring-like applications or rather if
they are then they're going to spend a
lot longer doing it than their
colleagues but what we're seeing is
there's growth elsewhere it's even
actually being reused or reinstituted
sorry in a number of cases as a teaching
language the the landscape on teaching
languages is no longer as clear as it
used to be that the field has muddied a
bit some people are exploring the use of
dynamic languages other universities are
sticking very much with their job of
curriculum some have favoured a c-sharp
and so on
but some have actually re taken the
decision to go C++ partly because
they're finding that it although it's
complex it offers them more of what they
want to teach computer science graduates
you can point pretty much anything and
that's a figurative statement as well as
a literal one you've mentioned this a
couple of times now that C's plus C++ is
viable for things you cannot do with
some other languages what is so special
about the language what is what's what
about its range of features and what
makes it applicable to a wider range of
features or of problems be it for
implementation be it at the teaching
level partly its its history every
language has a history and a soft spot
and therefore
where C++ comes from his is one is one
thing to say that C++ evolved from C and
that statement is certainly true but it
it fails to tell you why and it fails to
tell you what the focus was and the
focus there pianist Rastro was
originally looking at this it was
it's a systems language that is one he
wanted to express this is what he wanted
to provide a systems language that had
facilities that were more sophisticated
than those available in C which was the
system's language of emerging choice at
the time late 70s early 80s and so from
that point of view he wanted to be able
to talk about programs from a slightly
different perspective although C gives
us a structured programming language
with the basic sort of notions of
structured data indirection allows us to
abstract the specifics of the machine to
the point that we are talking about
pointers and not addresses and there's a
there's a whole load of pain that you no
longer have to go through having been a
systems programmer in Fortran the move
to C was a welcome relief so a better
alignment so we had that with C now what
is it that C++ gives us well it gives us
continues that progression why merely
have structured data when we can have a
more a rich vocabulary and say our
program is composed of stuff stuff has
behavior and recognize that we want
constructs that allow us to freely
change our minds about data structure if
we're talking about a systems language
it's actually quite important to have
that as it were byte level control but
it's also important to be able to change
your mind given that data structure
volatility you know okay that was a good
idea but let's change the data structure
but I still want the same operations but
how do I do that and not incur an
abstraction penalty so that notion has
always been there so to go back to the
question what we see is that the
tradition of C++ is as a systems
language a systems language is a
language in which you can build pretty
much anything that and and you can
control the parameters that you care
about now that obviously means that you
have a great deal of power it doesn't
necessarily mean that it is the right
tool for every job it doesn't
necessarily mean that every job is easy
but it ultimately means that every job
is possible at that level it does also
bring with it a certain culture which is
why you don't see C++ developers
necessarily pursuing the same interests
and framework styles as you find in
other in other spaces such as Java and
c-sharp and there's a very rich world of
open-source software where we see both
activity but also differences we see
some very big differences in focus so
I'm not actually interested in seeing
C++ developers trying to create an
spring-like frameworks or anything like
that I'm much more interested in working
with its sweet spot which is that that
area of systems programming I don't
really want to teach people to script in
C++ we've already got perfectly good
languages for that but if you if you
start thinking about wanting to create
the plumbing for an image processing
system I probably want to be expressing
my algorithms in C++ okay you've been
talking about this evolution C++ as a
systems language that used to be or what
does what used to be done in C and how
was what was the evolution actually I
mean simplify started as a preprocessor
front and for C if I recall correctly
but then sort of evolved away from that
with standard standardization process
what were those those steps and where is
it today I think we can characterize the
history of C++ in
I used to characterize it in three ages
but we're now reaching the point where
it's worth starting to think about
characterizing and for edges if we start
off with the earliest stage the the
stage that goes from really the creation
of the language through to the late 80s
around circa 1990 this early stage was
characterized by the original name of
the language see with classes and the
idea although one can look at it in
terms of a preprocessor it was well it
has always pretty much been a compiled
language is just chooses to spit out
chose to spit out sorry it's C code at
the back end originally in this at the
AT&T what came to be the AT&T C front
compiler now in that point of view the
primary approach there that was favored
was a style of object orientation sort
of borrowed from similar that Garrett
was characterized by say single
inheritance sort of simple
public-private model presence of classes
and virtual functions and features such
as that a few other little ideas
borrowed in from alcohol 68 and some
operator overloading things like that
all served up as it were on a sort of a
C infrastructure and sort of classic
source file model that existed and
continues to exist and that really
characterizes the early age of C++ now
it starts coming into its own right
people start tackling certain problems
they understands the style of a language
every language has a style and a way of
designing that is encouraged and what
emerged was the there were other aspects
there were other regularity aspects and
the language the there were ideas that
took us into history where the second
age of C++ which is gradually when it
grew most although templates and
exceptions were sort of there they were
they were sort of not as widely
supported and what we can actually say
is that in this period of the second and
second
C++ the there was the greatest diversity
in portability or well but another point
having lived through it lack of
portability that was the biggest problem
that divergence between various
compilers but part of that was learning
what the language felt like to be on its
own little things like the introduction
of new fundamental types because
overloading makes it a different
language to see you can no longer merely
say that boolean czar like can be like
integers and vice versa you actually
have to distinguish between the matter
in a kameena compile time fashion
because that is the character of the
language other aspects multiple
inheritance were introduced
let me think we had pure virtual
functions allowing abstract classes so a
lot more things started creeping in from
people's design thinking and realization
of what a C++ system might look like as
it grew larger so it was a working with
the language gave feedback on that but
there was also this rate of change now
because solid ations hatton him the
third age of C++ what characterizes
modern C++ which really is sort of 1997
1998 onwards the what characterizes this
period is the standard the standard
library the international standard of
the language this presence has actually
made quite a big difference to the way
that people perceive it and many people
have been surprised by how successful
its and this has been helping to
converge over time the divergent
platforms that we had there was a lot of
C++ compatibility issues so I mentioned
before this has made a big difference it
also helped influence people to
recognizing that the language in its own
right historically people used to teach
C++ kind of the way they learnt it they
learned C then they learned objects then
they learn C with objects so to speak
and as the language evolved they would
teach you the moral they teach you the
features in the order that they learnt
them very good example of this is the
introduction of
templates although they were introduced
early they came into their own and
really found their style and space
through the standardization of the
language and that and things like
standard template library really
characterized that now what we find is
that historically in the early 90s
people would put if they were authors
would write books on C++ and the last
chapter would probably be on templates
training courses would do follow a
similar idea and templates of either on
the Advanced Course you never do that on
the introductory course and you'd have
styles like that and then the they
denied me a chapter on the standard
library as that started emerging and
that would probably be in one of the
appendices or maybe one of the last
chapters if he would taught this in that
order which is actually quite peculiar
because many of these things if I had to
walk be merchants what we actually saw
in that period was a shift from C
programmers moving to C++ to non C
programmers with a very different
background people that looked at
pointers not as a natural mode of
expression and syntax but with some
suspicion and fright so you suddenly
realized okay this is a different
constituency and we have and in the
library we have a simple string type
okay so to not be talked the string type
until last thing was a very curious
thing but again it was historical it
sort of makes it harder to write hello
world oh there were lots of challenges
to a hello world and and goodbye C++ was
the immediate response of many people it
was a very it was a quite a strange time
where people were realigning themselves
and saying well actually the way to
teach C++ is to teach C++ not follow
this historical progression is no
denying that there is complexity in some
of the templates stuff but at the same
time there's no denying that there is
complexity in any feature the simple
template stuff is simple the hard
template stuff is hard so instead of
shoving it at the back of the course you
bring it to the front and I was involved
in training company in the late 90s
where we sort of
dealt with this issue we turned it
around one of the first courses to
actually do this to actually teach from
day one here's a string object and don't
worry about the underlying strings types
we'll get to chant pointers later and
here is a vector and don't worry about
what those angle brackets are just read
it as off so that's a vector event what
can you do well you can resize it can
you okay that's good can you can you
assign it yes you can it does everything
you expect can you subscript it does it
know how big it is the answers to all of
the above are yes so we start with that
idea and you don't need to teach
templates that level it's this notion of
usage versus plumbing and you don't need
to be a plumber in order to use a tap so
the point that has emerged since is that
many there are many many people who have
approached C++ from a historically very
different perspective from the one where
many people went off and explored other
languages and that Third Age has also
coincided with a growth of networking
software and a growth of embedded
software and so on which is one of the
things that has helped keep C++ sort of
fairly alive and popular but not in a
way that is actually I put it sexy and
fashionable yeah it's not necessarily
sexy in fashionable but as with fashion
if we look at if we look at the world of
fashion for inspiration because it is
somewhat like software development when
we find that there is somebody walking
on a catwalk and we see what they're
wearing it is very unlikely that the
regular person in the street will be
wearing that although it's where the
news is it's not what people are
actually wearing people are wearing
jeans and t-shirts and they are getting
on with things that solve that
particular problem space and and
sometimes that is a C++ sometimes it is
obscure homegrown languages sometimes it
is java sometimes it is one of a
thousand different scripting languages
it may even be COBOL but it's the jeans
and t-shirts that's where it is which
brings us to the fourth H which is the
the next standard the next standard is
in the process of being finalized we're
looking at 2009 and introduced is based
on experience not only a larger range of
libraries but also some language core
language enhancements mostly well from
anybody else's point of view it'll
mostly be in the area of templates and
the type system that templates deal with
and again that will give rise to a
different style and a different approach
and we can characterize that as it were
as a 1/4 age that's coming we're
planning a separate episode on that
quite interesting topic but it sort of
goes beyond the scope of what we're
talking about now that saves me a bit of
hassle and that beyond I can get to talk
about it we can also set them up quite
nicely here because what is interesting
the way I used to characterize the first
three ages of C++ as they roughly
correspond to an edition of be honest
book the first second and third edition
so I'm now legally awaiting the fourth
edition and opion is working on another
book at the moment but he's got a couple
of years to catch up on the air standard
okay but you mentioned a couple of the
features now and I know you long enough
to well be pretty sure that you that C++
is one of the languages that you love so
looking at these different types of
things you can do with C++ I mean it's a
multi paradigm language why don't we
take a look at some of the features and
you tell us what's great about them
what's special about them how
differentiate C++ from what you've been
doing more boring more down-to-earth
languages that may look sexier but don't
get the job done as well so let's start
with templates so what's great about
templates the length of the error
messages okay that's the cynical
response yeah let's let's get that one
out of the way templates can be
potentially challenging what is what is
great about templates well they're worth
we can talk about we can state a number
of facts here's a couple of facts the
template system is actually a
turing-complete you can actually it's a
programmable system it's an interesting
side effect it was never really intended
but you can perform calculations in it
this allows you to do things at compile
time
that gives you no runtime overhead it
allows you to express and use the same
kinds of a abstraction sophistication at
compile time that don't you don't really
want to sit in the runtime or would
traditionally be done in another
language or external to external
configuration tool obviously the
downside to this is the subtlety in some
of the expressions and also some of the
sophistication you need to have to
understand what's going on and the
ability to read angle brackets but given
the prevalence of XML these days are
less concerned about that for now used
to be so boards down to templates are
great because they allow you compile
time optimizations of performance of
memory footprint that you wouldn't be
able to have otherwise because because
you'd have to have the generalization in
the code and it incurred the runtime
overhead that's part of it but there's
also something more than that it's
actually it's not just the it's not just
a speed factor it's the ability to
express certain ideas relationships
between types in a compile time way we
can actually see perhaps one of the ways
of looking at the templates I mean only
when people say templates the the usual
expectation is that somebody's going to
talk about containers yes this is all
certainly true the container library and
many aspects like smart pointers we rely
on those for templating but the that is
basic generics that's sort of your
introductory level generics this is the
kind of thing that people normally think
of as being generics let's put it this
way that is the beginning of the idea of
a generic system not the end where as
many languages in spite of the
experience that it is around about using
their generic type systems many
languages introduced generic type system
when it stops pretty much with the the
collections and things and it doesn't go
much further what you haven't C++ is
that that is just the beginning so the
notion I've just described all this
other stuff is meta programming at the
template level
I wouldn't necessarily encourage
everybody to do it and I spent a great
deal of time discouraging people from do
it it is it is can be frightening ly
obscure at times and also surprisingly
unnecessary but
at all when it's needed it does offer
you the way of describing at
compile-time relationships between types
values that you need something that
other languages have a capability for
through runtime reflection but what
we're talking about here is as it were a
compile time for you and perhaps that's
the best way of looking at the C++
template system it is a static version
of what many people see in dynamic type
air dynamically typed languages it is
based on a historically is based on duck
typing for want of a better term the the
notion of the notion that if it looks
like a duck and sounds like a duck and
it waddles like a duck then it's a duck
it you no longer have to say that to
perform the capability of a foo you have
to inherit from class foo you just say
if it looks like it does foo then it
does foo so that is the notion that we
have but it's what somebody wants
described as frozen small talk what it's
done is its frozen at compile time of
course that doesn't give you the general
flexibility but it does give you some of
them for some of the things that people
want and they want them at compile time
given that there is a notion of compile
time and they want them in a way that
allows them to control the bits the
bytes the performance and so on and
these are the people that care then
having this mechanism is incredibly
powerful the challenge is that the
language was not originally designed for
this or the temperature the template
mechanism was not originally designed
for this so it strains a little to
express some of the concepts and it
requires certain amount of ingenuity and
you can see some of that ingenuity in a
variety of publications and also a
certain amount of published code and
such as the most libraries in order to
make these things work that what we're
seeing in the next generation of C++ is
an acknowledgment of the power of these
but also a type system as it were one of
the things that most duck type systems
suffer from and this I refer to dynamic
languages as well as the statically
compiled ones is there's no duck I'm
unable to point to the duck and name
the dark I merely I it's an idea I
cannot name it within the programming
system so it's really a type system for
templates that we're looking at in the
future but that notion of templates
allows the expression of things like the
standard template library and it's a
radically different style of programming
it's not a sort of classic oo
style at all and to be I guess to be
honest if the STL hadn't come along is
unlikely I would still be doing C++
there's really weird stuff you can do
with C++ templates that go way beyond
for example the Java generics which are
well something entirely different but in
C++ you can for example inherit the
class can inherit from a template
parameter do you know of any example
where that is used for yeah there's a
number of frameworks where what you're
effectively trying to do is take a class
and inject behavior into its base class
and this has been used in a few places
there's examples can be found in
Microsoft's ATL where what you're doing
is you provide a base you provide some
kind of class and it's parameterised
with respect to something else that it
inherits from it gets these features as
we're at a patents conference it's
probably appropriate to point out that
the this technique is very similar to an
idea of template method whereas
traditionally the template method
pattern can be expressed using a base
class where you provide some hooks for
behavior and you provide a well-defined
method which has got some kind of
algorithm in C++ what you can do is
freeze this a compile time so it's not
the runtime performance that I'm after I
don't want a runtime hook method in that
sense my member functions are actually
well known these situation is well
defined with with respect it's framework
I don't want any runtime lookup I want a
distinct and definite type that I want
to manipulate and what you do is you
allow yourself to put the behavior into
the base class and and notionally
override it upside down by using this
technique so yes
applications of this technique and I
this is it's a surprising one when you
first see it it's not a technique I
would expect to see in every application
but at the same time it's not something
that is obscure or academic there's
genuinely practical applications over
here another controversial feature in
C++ is operator overloading what's your
take on that is it useful or does it do
more harm than it is good well there's a
number of different ways of looking at
this one
first of all let's understand what it is
that you get for your money with
operator overloading you are talking
about taking the existing set of
operators in the language and being able
to overload them four types that you
have defined or someone is defined and
provide appropriate behavior for them
things you cannot do is extend the range
of operators in the language there are
some languages that allow you to do this
and it is not proven to be useful it
allows people to go off and create their
own private dialects better known as ET
elects where one person thinks it's an
absolutely brilliant idea to add an
operator to a language and everybody
else thinks it's one of the craziest
things out and it reduces the
comprehensibility of code so no c++
doesn't allow you to do that of course
it does allow you to get kind of a bit
clever and the point is there's no
constraint on the semantics you provide
for your operator overloads but c++ is
actually in the majority of languages as
it were that have popularity these days
there are very few languages that don't
support some form of operator
overloading even scripting languages are
actually more able to do this than many
mainstream languages a few years ago the
desire to not support operator
overloading was motivated and carried
through in Java partly because you can
indeed write obscure code and you met
you can end up with some crazy stuff
where somebody goes a plus B minus C and
you look at that and you think okay
one-way looking at all right what you're
looking at is a database transaction and
then the final commits it's like no no I
don't see that of course
this does not stop yeah oh this is this
is not really a very sound objection for
a number of reasons first of all I've
seen a lot of code I do code reviews and
I've seen code in various languages and
I'm impressed with what people are able
to do with just ordinary named functions
that completely mislead and hide their
meaning so what is it that operator
overloading is supposed to give me
what's the value proposition if I want
to add two things together that are
intrinsically a double they are value
types of some kind whether they
represent money monetary quantities
whether they represent physical
quantities measurements and so on then
and I want to add them then I want to
see a plus B I do not want to see a dot
and brackets B brackets I want to see a
plus B plus C I do not want to see a dot
add brackets B dot and bracket C close
brackets and I don't want to see this
kind of stuff it's clumsy and I'm wheel
D and advocates of this position have
very little to stand on for a very
simple point of view I have a
five-year-old son and he can read up
here he can read a plus symbol and he
knows what it means and he can't spell
plus he can't spell addition he can't
spell subtraction but he knows what a
minus sign is and he's got a rough idea
of what it might mean
so he's five years old and he's able to
understand these operators apparently
there are a bunch of people at son who
don't think that developers understand
this stuff and it's a little bit
patronizing from my point of view much
as I love the Java language it is a bit
patronizing if I want to add two
concepts together I want to be given the
operator there's already a name for the
idea it's not a DD and there's a plus
symbol for it if I want to subscript
into something that represents a
collection of things that is based on a
key or an index I want to use my square
brackets because that's what the
language says I talked earlier on of a
language having start a particular style
and when I'm working with our language
then subscript subscript is the way of
doing that plus is the way of doing
certain things assignment is the way of
doing others the arrow operator is the
way of accessing a level of indirection
plus plus is the way I'm
move to the next thing whatever it is
the next thing is in a sequence there's
a set of conventions that govern this
and of course people can try to go
against conventions there are cases
where this works but most cases don't
there are this is what this is more
about development process and
development maturity than it is about
the language I think people incorrectly
blame the language of these features now
I will just close or close that
discussion on operator overloading with
some of the more that some of the wilder
uses and actually say that in some cases
these are justified there is a minority
of cases where almost creating a private
language does make sense and the current
growth the current growth in the idea of
domain-specific languages and also in
particular embedded or internal to most
specific languages where we create a
sort of mini language within a language
can actually go it goes back decades
certainly to the list community but has
been represented in some one a more
powerful languages over time the current
language of choice many people is Ruby
but it's this history also exists within
C++ and the idea is that the template
facilities combined with many of the
operator overloading facilities allowing
you to create effectively a private
domain-specific language in the context
of C++ and there's a great deal
exploration of this the generative
programming book a few years ago sort of
demonstrated some of the techniques and
at this point there are a number of
libraries that express certain ideas
that are well let me pick on a very
simple on the boost spirit library is a
language in which you can define the
grammar of a language and pause it now
traditionally this will be done by
separating out your tools your Lex and
yak your antlers or whatever and having
different build steps now I can actually
represent the syntax of language and
something that actually looks like BNF
in C++ and actually treat that as an
object compose my syntax treated as an
object hook events to it and basically
run a parser off this now that's pretty
cool there are this use of I understand
the Martin Fowler we joined the term a
couple of years ago fluid interfaces
where you have this ability to chain
things when you have chain method calls
when you have a language that supports
operator overloading in templates you
can do this quite extensively and
there's a great deal of experience in
the sort of a certain parts of the C++
world in creating libraries in this
particular style but of course there is
always the question of taste and
judgment and that can sometimes push
operator overloading just a little bit
too far
okay another of the controversial
features in C++ is multiple
implementation inheritance
what's you take on that I don't
particularly have a great problem with
it but it used to be one of these issues
that would polarize people in a very
strong way sort of you know do you use V
or Emacs kind of question you know
without any ration our people would get
very very hot under the collar
multiple inheritance makes things
certainly more complex in the language
from the point of view of the compiler
writer and it makes things it can make
things more complex from the point of
view of the developer if the developer
does not have a reasoned way of thinking
about multiple inheritance and applying
it then they are looking at it as a just
a language mechanism they're not really
thinking about it as a design tool in
truth I find I don't really use multiple
inheritance of implementation very much
at all and I would struggle to think of
many cases where I do the style that is
popular in language design say from
early mid-90s onwards and we see it
manifested in Java and c-sharp is that
you have a dominant
class and then you have interfaces that
are mixed in I find that I use that
style quite a lot and occasionally my
mix-ins will have a little bit of
behavior but not often and that's partly
to do with the style of design and an
approach and having a clear sort of
design style and vision what people who
have struggled with with multiple
inheritance is that they were originally
presented with multiple inheritance as
an implementation idea they were given
it as a mechanism here is a language
feature and if you take that that's kind
of designing the wrong way around it
doesn't solve a problem I it's a case if
I'm wandering around with the solution
that has a lot of mechanics and plumbing
and I'm looking for ways to apply it and
that I have certainly seen that in code
bases I'm probably guilty of having used
that many many many years ago but I
would always advocate the ability to be
able to multiple it not be inherited
even though I would not advocate its
common use it's the idea that in some
cases when you are trying to bring
together two pieces of code that this is
one of the more discreet ways of doing
it and the ability to do non public
inheritance is what makes this very
practical approach a lot of what you've
been saying sounds to me like C++ gives
you a wide range of powerful tools just
don't use them all the time so it sounds
to me like C+ and C++ idioms the
knowledge of how to actually use the
language features is particularly
important maybe even more important than
other languages yes I would definitely
agree this is the I in in recent talks
over the last year or so I've started
using the quote from spider-man with
great power comes great responsibility
and I am very I'm I'm quite I I guess
black and white on this and I would say
that for many people
I wouldn't recommend C++ and I wouldn't
recommend it for all problems at all I
can't recommend it in many many cases
because it is a complex language
criticality of knowledge is that much
higher for C++ than it is many other
mainstream languages
it doesn't mean that you can't make a
mess in other mainstream languages I
like I said I'm an independent
consultant and I to work in languages
other than C++ you can make a mess it's
just the criticality the value that a
particular level of knowledge has in C++
that distinguishes between successful
design and unsuccessful design is that
much more important and the bar is that
much higher you are given of a wide
variety of features and many of them as
it where are they sharp tools of the
language and get it wrong you cut
yourself badly and this notion is that
as you say the mastery of the idioms the
familiarity with the approaches and
techniques does require some study and
some recognition it's not a language you
can walk into and be productive from day
zero on it's doesn't have necessarily
that characteristic but once you have
reached a particular level you are
likely to be you're likely to find
yourself thinking quite fluidly in it
and once you've reached that level then
its gain that kind of you passed through
the gate the language is irrelevant then
you know you in principle you could
master any language from that point
so yes the idioms and this is one of the
interesting things in C++ is this
reliance on things that are beyond the
language and beyond the library this
world of knowledge that here at the
patins conference we try and capture imp
and form but has been captured in in
different narratives and arc article
styles and book contexts pretty much
from the outset certainly characterized
the second age of C++ one of those
idioms that what when I came back when I
did C++ that was one of the important
idioms was the canonical form it was
sort of lots of things to remember to do
consistently and easy to forget so are
there now ways to sort of do that in in
one place and have it reused or have
that checked or something or it's does
it still require this knowledge all over
the place
there is still a case of having to know
what you're expecting but things have
actually got simpler the the kind of
Orthodox canonical class form is not
necessarily a solution to a problem it
is a regular set of things that are
probably there it was almost done it's
almost like a checklist what we've what
we've discovered over time is there are
actually easier ways of expressing some
of the ideas and the relationships
between the operators and certain
operations maybe you could just probably
explain what this canonical form is
about yes
this form was originally identified by
Jim Killeen and his book Atman C++
programming styles and idioms and and
this is the book I had in mind when I
said that the second era of C++ was
characterized by focus on idioms of that
nature and this Orthodox canonical class
form focuses on what am I expecting in
my class interface and it's primarily
about the operators destructors and
constructors and the relationships
between them it's become more apparent
that there are other idioms that we
really want to apply for example it's
fairly unlikely than most classes should
have an assignment operator or a copy
constructor and they are not things that
classes that represent entities or
service style objects do not really have
value semantics that are useful or
meaningful and therefore we would
normally find such objects on the heap
we might allocate them on the heap
ourselves we might get a factory to do
it we might do it in a number of
different ways but these objects may
also express express polymorphically and
again there are a number of challenges
for people trying to do assignment with
polymorphic types in class hierarchies
the simple summaries don't do it so the
nature of idiomatic practice in C++
hasn't many ways got simpler because
originally people were looking at how do
I fashion the tools and now people who
look at it the other way round is like
what is the problem I am solving and
organizing the language features around
that the columns that I used to write
for briefly for C++ purport and then for
cuj online
we're entitled from mechanism to method
and that was kind of a reaction to the
fact that people focused on mechanisms
for using the language features what I'm
interested in is okay what is the thing
that we are building I'm expressing an
object that has the following
characteristics not C++ characteristics
but domain characteristics from that I
can say this object is not assignable we
have idioms for expressing nor no sign
ability indeed if we look a little
further afield we also have libraries
that express that it is possible to
inherit the non copyable capability I am
NOT copyable at all and Express that at
the class level so there are a number of
different ideas there that allow us to
think about our classes in a different
way this applies to assignment most most
classes probably not meaningfully
assignable but also when we start
working with libraries that are based on
value semantics such as the STL what we
also find is that for all of those
classes where we do want meaningful copy
semantics it's already been taken care
off for us so there is a there's less
attention paid to how do i construct
this class in this particular way when
I'm allocating loads of things on the
heap and I need to manage my resources
more of these are encapsulated so you
just write the class the copy behavior
comes for free and is correct the
destruction behavior comes for free and
is correct so that kind of distinguishes
again this is one of those things about
the criticality of knowledge and also
the way we teach the language if we look
at somebody working with 1990s C++ style
and idioms the chances are they are
struggling more than they need to it's
it's it's sort of a wasted challenge in
that sense they're doing more manual
memory management than they need to they
are worrying more about how their
pointers are flying than they need to
they are worrying more about which old
idioms to apply where new idioms simply
express things in terms of libraries or
better encapsulated types so I
understanding how to encapsulate types
the value based programming has improved
as well so the idiom landscape has
definitely shifted
there's nothing that will necessarily
automatically check things there are
various tools that will check for the
usual bits and pieces likely memory
corruption and so on but what we're
really looking at is capturing a style
in the midst of all the possibilities
that actually makes sense and it can be
considered to be relatively simple and
this these styles do exist you see some
surprisingly short and elegant pieces of
code that years ago people would have
expressed and ten times the size let's
take a look at C++ culture arm one of
the things that I always found weird
what the C++ culture is though
obfuscated C++ contests do they still
exist or has a language sort of outgrown
them well technically we can actually
argue that the contest never really
existed but there were because
historically there was the International
office gated C coding contest but it was
never deemed appropriate to do a C++ one
because it would be dropped there's no
challenge
it is very easy to create an obscure it
is very easy to create an obscure code
in C++ and there's no denying that and
we can go back to the earlier
conversation we were having about
operator overloading it is it's not a
hard thing to do
hopefully that people aren't thinking of
their code though is a sort of
executable line noise we don't really
want to recreate Perl in the land of C++
what we're looking at is the focus
sometimes though is on cleverness and
techniques I would say that's a very
strong aspect of the core C++ culture
and I don't think that is necessarily
particularly healthy and that's
something I find myself often critical
of and a number although I spoke
favorably of template metaprogramming
earlier on I actually spend a lot of
time discouraging people from this not
because it's a bad idea it's just that
it's not a generally applicable idea
it's a it's an idea that has a very very
good soft spot beyond which you really
don't want to be doing this stuff you
will create solutions that are so clever
that your colleagues will just be
stunned into silence
and you have therefore created a job for
life nobody else can maintain this code
there are certainly plenty of cleverness
around there's sometimes an obsession
with performance often obsession with
micro optimization at the expense of
architectural thinking I find in the C++
culture that it is a case of the people
under many people understand the cost of
particular operations but they do not
know the value of their particular
designs and when we look a little
further there are aspects at the C++
culture that have moved forward and
embraced things like generic programming
which is not simply Chilean programming
templates it is it's a misapplication of
the word generic for which Alex stepping
off the event of STL has apologised for
it's a general approach that is based on
an our emphasis on algorithms and data
structures and the separation thereof
and it's a generalized approach that
gives rise to libraries like the STL
many of the boost libraries and so on
and is markedly different from other
library styles and language styles that
we see and in terms of our approach to
things it is not a particularly a
classic object-oriented style although
it relies on some of the similar
concepts but in that culture there is a
strong focus on the importance of
algorithms and the emphasis on economy
of expression however this is sometimes
at the expense of some of the other
things that I personally value which is
sort of larger scale architecture and
appreciation of systems thinking so
curiously we are at a patins conference
and I find that in the C++ world the
level of pattern knowledge is
surprisingly no or rather it is it has
plateaued and it plateaued with the Gang
of Four book which is sort of 13 years
ago and there is still a sort of C++
developers they haven't really moved
beyond the idea that there are 23
patterns ok this is a terrible
characterization there are
those of you out there that will
certainly have done this but just my
usual sampling of various conferences
and a show of hand sampling suggests
that C++ developers have not really
followed this through and they're kind
of stuck with sometimes a design style
in a way of thinking about their designs
that disconnects from modern C++ style
and modern C++ capabilities but also
disconnects from broader appreciation of
architecture there are other aspects in
C++ culture there is an emphasis on and
a care for dependency management many
people are particularly aware of that
now this matters in any language but
it's critical in C++ but it tends to
sharpen people people's outlook on how
they relate to their classes at the same
time there is a flip side to this one
and that is that there are still certain
cultural memes as it were that still
propagate there's still a lot more
inheritance heavy codes and I would
expect to see this is although we talk
about a modern C++ style that's not part
of it but there is the majority of code
is written in this style partly from
history and people are strongly
influenced by that there are some
terrible examples of libraries out there
sort of one mainstream adoption NFC is
probably the leading example this is
we've been handed down design decisions
that didn't look particularly good when
they were introduced in the early 90s
and anyone that was a C++ developer who
knew this would have pointed that out
but has become a mainstream thing and
actually probably caused more problems
than its solved and there are different
ways of dealing with questions of
framework design so again this comes
back to a design culture aspect so
design is valued in C++ very very much
but it tends to be a slightly different
style and way of thinking of design than
many are now pursuing and then not only
in other languages but in other system
architectural styles many people in C++
are using these and they are getting
benefit from these but I
probably I guess the greater majority
have not had the opportunity to catch up
how would you characterize the role of
microsoft visual c++ and the MFC in the
with the overall c++ landscape is it
sort of two different cultures how are
they related are they different it has
been very influential on a number of
levels
the Microsoft's involved with C++ has
been very on and off over the years and
unfortunately in recent years has been
very on I think they'll be the best way
of putting learning that the
historically Microsoft introduced a very
modest compiler and they weren't first
into the C++ compiler space it was a
very modest set of capabilities and not
a bad first effort and I was Microsoft C
C++ 7 the precursor of Visual C++ 1 and
it wasn't bad for the time but then they
failed to do the basic thing which is
actually upgrade it and update it so
people were left with a very first age
view of C++ for a large part of the
early 90s and there were there were some
leaps forward in the compiler and the
environment at around that time and that
looks pretty good then it sort of
plateaued again at around visual C++ 6
which state which has become a sort of
compatibility non-standard if you like
it's become a a chain around the necks
of many developers because it is
actually has quite poor compatibility
with the standard and has been used for
a lot of code and the fortunate story
gets better Microsoft have a much more
engaged C++ team now their conformance
the conformance their compiler is pretty
good it used to be a case that you
wouldn't trust a Microsoft compiler I
tend to use it all the time now so
there's been a real shift the language
has been adopted more positively the
compiler compiles the language as
opposed to someone somebody else's idea
for language and so we have that aspect
so the compiler is very influential the
that when they sort of offered the an
edition of the compiler for download for
free that was quite influential as well
a lot of people now have access to the
basic set of tools so this is all the
this is all the good stuff with sort of
some footnotes for me the bad side has
always been the MFC I have when I first
encountered it back in 1992 I was
underwhelmed by the design expertise
that had gone into it it looked kind of
like a thin wrapper written by a C
programmer with a VB background on top
of the Windows API which is kind of what
it was really and it's kind of grown
from now it's grown into a sort of whole
industry of itself
now it's not to say the library is not
without use or and it's not without
intricacy in detail and there are a
number of techniques in there that can
be adopted elsewhere but it is created a
sort of a sort of a much larger training
industry in a much larger book industry
and a much larger support industry than
it should have done and it also
introduces a number of things that are
more complex and putting together a new
AI in MFC is not necessarily a
particularly painless experience to get
the most out of UI design in NFC
actually requires you to know quite a
lot about the underlying api so in that
sense it's a we can see that it's not a
successful encapsulation it's a facade
of that level you find yourself
sometimes struggling with defaults and
the approach to trying to create a DSL
within the language through the use of
macros and the support of wizards has
only been partially successful and
indeed a colleague of mine once
described the Wizards as saucers
apprentices because really they they
introduced things that cause you
problems they seemed to compensate
for things that should be in the library
so yes I am being highly critical of MFC
here and unashamedly so and I know that
some in Microsoft regard is a blot on
the history when they started doing
things like the ATL route that
highlighted a better level of
sophistication and understanding of what
you can do with C++ okay one last
question I have the impression that you
love C++ any final words you'd like to
say about what you love about C++ why
you think it's a great language or
anything else you'd like to add before
we wrap up I think the anything else
you'd like to add up before a wrap up is
I do like I do like using multiple
languages but I do have a particular
soft spot as you've noticed for C++ but
not an irrationally driven one I deal
with a lot of languages things I like
about C++ well obviously there's a
certain comfort and familiarity it is
other than I would say the only other
language that I might compile code in
that I've been using as long as probably
C but I don't use C on its own very much
so it's probably the language I have
used longest continuously and the only
way that any other language will be able
to compete with that is where I actively
don't use C++ for five or six years than
Java will become the next one but yes I
do enjoy using there is a high degree of
familiarity the familiarity also comes
from the work that I used to do where
really knowing the inside out detail of
the stand and the language made a lot of
sense but again it's the sense that I
can apply the language to a number of
problems and again the kind of problems
that some of my customers deal with they
they deal with things where you are
actually you care a great deal about the
performance the bits of the bytes and
that level of control and so I enjoy
working in that space the frustration
for me comes from the other aspects of
C++ culture and the accidental complex
the language brings with it that we find
to find the good design takes probably
more effort than it does elsewhere and I
find the they the pleasurable experience
of just being able to easily involve
tests a simple design in other languages
is sometimes lacking from the experience
of my clients in C++ although I would
say I have a relatively similar
experience in C++ because I write my
code in a way that can it does that
that's not the experience shared by many
people so in as in the sense that I love
sleepless yes I'd like to share that
experience more widely and and encourage
people to sort of pursue a slightly more
economic and more modern style in that
sense thank you very much thank you all
right
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and /not
buttons to contact the team lease an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot site music network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle